Business generates those resources when it makes a profit. That profit is that small difference between the price and the cost it takes to produce whatever solution business has created to whatever problem they're trying to solve. But that profit is the magic. Why? Because that profit allows whatever solution we've created to be infinitely scalable. Because if we can make a profit, we can do it for 10, 100, a million, 100 million, a billion. The solution becomes self-sustaining. That's what business does when it makes a profit. Now what does this all have to do with social problems? Well, one line of thinking is, let's take this profit and redeploy it into social problems. Business should give more. Business should be more responsible. And that's been the path that we've been on in business. But again, this path that we've been on is not getting us where we need to go. Now, I started out as a strategy professor, and I'm still a strategy professor. I'm proud of that. But I've also, over the years, worked more and more on social issues. I've worked on healthcare, the environment, economic development, reducing poverty, and as I worked more and more in the social field, I started seeing something that had a profound impact on me and my whole life, in a way. The conventional wisdom in economics and the view in business has historically been that actually, there's a tradeoff between social performance and economic performance. The conventional wisdom has been that business actually makes a profit by causing a social problem. The classic example is pollution. If business pollutes, it makes more money than if it tried to reduce that pollution. Reducing pollution is expensive, therefore businesses don't want to do it. It's profitable to have an unsafe working environment. It's too expensive to have a safe working environment, therefore business makes more money if they don't have a safe working environment. That's been the conventional wisdom. A lot of companies have fallen into that conventional wisdom. They resisted environmental improvement. They resisted workplace improvement. That thinking has led to, I think, much of the behavior that we have come to criticize in business, that I come to criticize in business. But the more deeply I got into all these social issues, one after another, and actually, the more I tried to address them myself, personally, in a few cases, through nonprofits that I was involved with, the more I found actually that the reality is the opposite. Business does not profit from causing social problems, actually not in any fundamental sense. That's a very simplistic view. The deeper we get into these issues, the more we start to understand that actually business profits from solving from social problems. That's where the real profit comes. Let's take pollution. We've learned today that actually reducing pollution and emissions is generating profit. It saves money. It makes the business more productive and efficient. It doesn't waste resources. Having a safer working environment actually, and avoiding accidents, it makes the business more profitable, because it's a sign of good processes. Accidents are expensive and costly. Issue by issue by issue, we start to learn that actually there's no trade-off between social progress and economic efficiency in any fundamental sense. Another issue is health. I mean, what we've found is actually health of employees is something that business should treasure, because that health allows those employees to be more productive and come to work and not be absent. The deeper work, the new work, the new thinking on the interface between business and social problems is actually showing that there's a fundamental, deep synergy, particularly if you're not thinking in the very short run. In the very short run, you can sometimes fool yourself into thinking that there's fundamentally opposing goals, but in the long run, ultimately, we're learning in field after field that this is simply not true. So how could we tap into the power of business to address the fundamental problems that we face? Imagine if we could do that, because if we could do it, we could scale. We could tap into this enormous resource pool and this organizational capacity. And guess what? That's happening now, finally, partly because of people like you who have raised these issues now for year after year and decade after decade. We see organizations like Dow Chemical leading the revolution away from trans fat and saturated fat with innovative new products. This is an example of Jain Irrigation. This is a company that's brought drip irrigation technology to thousands and millions of farmers, reducing substantially the use of water. We see companies like the Brazilian forestry company Fibria that's figured out how to avoid tearing down old growth forest and using eucalyptus and getting much more yield per hectare of pulp and making much more paper than you could make by cutting down those old trees. You see companies like Cisco that are training so far four million people in I.T. skills to actually, yes, be responsible, but help expand the opportunity to disseminate I.T. technology and grow the whole business. There's a fundamental opportunity for business today to impact and address these social problems, and this opportunity is the largest business opportunity we see in business. And the question is, how can we get business thinking to adapt this issue of shared value? This is what I call shared value: addressing a social issue with a business model. That's shared value. Shared value is capitalism, but it's a higher kind of capitalism. It's capitalism as it was ultimately meant to be, meeting important needs, not incrementally competing for trivial differences in product attributes and market share. Shared value is when we can create social value and economic value simultaneously. It's finding those opportunities that will unleash the greatest possibility we have to actually address these social problems because we can scale. We can address shared value at multiple levels. It's real. It's happening. But in order to get this solution working, we have to now change how business sees itself, and this is thankfully underway. Businesses got trapped into the conventional wisdom that they shouldn't worry about social problems, that this was sort of something on the side, that somebody else was doing it. We're now seeing companies embrace this idea. But we also have to recognize business is not going to do this as effectively as if we have NGOs and government working in partnership with business. The new NGOs that are really moving the needle are the ones that have found these partnerships, that have found these ways to collaborate. The governments that are making the most progress are the governments that have found ways to enable shared value in business rather than see government as the only player that has to call the shots. And government has many ways in which it could impact the willingness and the ability of companies to compete in this way. I think if we can get business seeing itself differently, and if we can get others seeing business differently, we can change the world. I know it. I'm seeing it. I'm feeling it. Young people, I think, my Harvard Business School students, are getting it. If we can break down this sort of divide, this unease, this tension, this sense that we're not fundamentally collaborating here in driving these social problems, we can break this down, and we finally, I think, can have solutions. Thank you. (Applause)
Los negocios generan esos recursos cuando obtienen ganancias. Esas ganancias son la pequeña diferencia entre el precio y los gastos necesarios para producir cualquier solución que haya creado una empresa para cualquier problema que tratan de resolver. Pero esa ganancia es la magia. ¿Por qué? Porque esa ganancia permite que cualquier solución que hayamos creado sea infinitamente escalable. Porque si podemos tener una ganancia, podemos multiplicarla por 10, por 100, por un millón, 100 millones, mil millones. La solución se vuelve autosostenible. Eso es lo que hacen los negocios cuando hay ganancia. Ahora, ¿qué tiene que ver todo esto con los problemas sociales? Bueno, una forma de pensar es tomar esa ganancia y redistribuirla a los problemas sociales. Las empresas deberían dar más. Las empresas deben ser más responsables. Ese ha sido el camino que hemos seguido en los negocios. Una vez más, el camino que hemos seguido no nos está llevando a donde tenemos que ir. Empecé como profesor de estrategia, y todavía lo soy. Estoy orgulloso de ello. Pero con los años, he trabajado cada vez más con problemas sociales. He trabajado en salud, en medio ambiente, en desarrollo económico, en la reducción de la pobreza, y mientras trabajaba cada vez más en el ámbito social comencé a ver algo que me impactó significativamente y repercutió en mi vida. La sabiduría convencional en economía y la visión de negocio ha sido históricamente la de que existe una compensación entre el desempeño social y el rendimiento económico. La sabiduría convencional nos dice que los negocios obtienen ganancias causando problemas sociales. El ejemplo clásico es la contaminación. Si el negocio contamina, gana más dinero que si intenta reducir esa contaminación. Reducir la contaminación es muy costoso, por eso las empresas no quieren hacerlo. Resulta rentable tener un entorno de trabajo poco seguro. Es demasiado caro tener un entorno de trabajo seguro, por eso los negocios ganan más si el entorno laboral no es seguro. Esa ha sido la idea convencional. Muchas empresas han caído en esa idea convencional. Se resisten a mejorar el medio ambiente. Se resisten a mejorar del entorno laboral. Esa forma de pensar ha conducido, creo, a buena parte del comportamiento que hemos llegado a criticar en los negocios, que yo mismo he llegado a criticar. Pero, cuanto más me metía en todos estos problemas sociales, uno tras otro, y en realidad, cuanto más intentaba hacerles frente, personalmente, en algunos casos, a través de organizaciones a las que pertenecía, estaba cada vez más convencido de que la realidad es todo lo contrario. Las empresas no obtienen ganancias causando problemas sociales, al menos no en sentido fundamental. Esa es una visión muy simplista. Cuanto más nos metemos en estos temas, mejor podemos entender que las empresas realmente generan ganancias cuando solucionan problemas sociales. De ahí viene la verdadera ganancia. Por ejemplo, la contaminación. Hemos aprendido hoy que en realidad reducir la contaminación y las emisiones genera ganancias. Ahorra dinero. Hace que el negocio sea más productivo y eficiente. No malgasta recursos. Tener un entorno de trabajo más seguro y evitar los accidentes, hace que el negocio sea más rentable, porque es una muestra de buenos procedimientos. Los accidentes son caros y costosos. Problema tras problema, empezamos a entender que en realidad no hay compensación entre el progreso social y la eficiencia económica en ningún sentido fundamental. Otra cuestión es la salud. Es decir, lo que hemos descubierto en realidad es que la salud de los empleados es algo que una empresa debe atesorar, porque la salud permite que esos empleados sean más productivos y puedan trabajar y no estén ausentes. El trabajo más profundo, el nuevo trabajo, el nuevo pensamiento en la interfaz entre las empresas y los problemas sociales; en realidad está demostrando que hay una sinergia fundamental y profunda, especialmente si no estás pensando en el corto plazo. En muy corto plazo, puedes a veces engañarte pensando que fundamentalmente hay objetivos opuestos, pero a la larga, en última instancia, estamos aprendiendo área tras área, que esto simplemente no es cierto. Entonces, ¿cómo podríamos usar el poder de los negocios para abordar los problemas fundamentales que enfrentamos? Imagínense que si podemos hacerlo, podríamos escalar. Podríamos aprovechar esta enorme reserva de recursos y esta capacidad organizativa. Y, adivinen qué. Está ocurriendo ahora mismo, finalmente. En parte gracias a personas como ustedes que están planteando estas cuestiones, año tras año y década tras década. Vemos a organizaciones como Dow Chemical liderando la revolución para eliminar las grasas trans y las grasas saturadas con productos nuevos e innovadores. Este es un ejemplo de Jain Irrigation. Esta es una empresa que ha traído la tecnología del riego por goteo a miles y millones de campesinos, reduciendo sustancialmente el uso de agua. Vemos a empresas como la compañía forestal brasileña Fibria que descubrió cómo evitar la tala de bosques antiguos. Usa el eucalipto y consigue mucho más rendimiento por hectárea de pulpa y produce más papel que lo podría lograr talando árboles viejos. Ves a empresas como Cisco que ha entrenado hasta el momento a 4 millones de personas en informática, siendo realmente responsable al ayudar a expandir las oportunidades al difundir la tecnología informática y hacer crecer toda la empresa. Hoy existe una oportunidad fundamental para las empresas de impactar y lidiar con estos problemas sociales. Esta oportunidad es la del negocio más grande que vemos en el mundo real. La pregunta es, ¿cómo hacer para que las empresas quieran adoptar el tema del valor compartido? Esto es lo que llamo valor compartido: Abordar un tema social con un modelo de negocio. Eso es valor compartido. Valor compartido es capitalismo, pero en su forma más avanzada. Es el capitalismo como debe ser verdaderamente, satisfaciendo necesidades importantes, sin competir por pequeñeces, por diferencias triviales en las características del producto y en las cuotas del mercado. Valor compartido es cuando podemos crear valor social y valor económico al mismo tiempo. Es encontrar esas oportunidades que desatarán nuestras mejores posibilidades para abordar problemas sociales porque así podemos escalar. Podemos abordar el valor compartido en muchos niveles. Es real. Está sucediendo. Pero para lograr que esta solución funcione, tenemos que cambiar la forma como las empresas se ven a sí mismas, y esto afortunadamente ya está en marcha. Muchas empresas se han quedado atrapadas en la idea convencional de que no deberían preocuparse por los problemas sociales, porque esto era algo periférico, que alguien más debería hacer. Ahora se ven empresas que aceptan la idea. Pero también tenemos que reconocer que las empresas no lo van a hacer con tanta eficacia si no logran que las ONGs y el gobierno trabajen en colaboración con ellas. Las nuevas ONGs que realmente hacen la diferencia son las que han conseguido estas cooperaciones, que han encontrado estas maneras de colaborar. Los gobiernos que han logrado un mayor avance son los que han encontrado maneras de habilitar el valor compartido en los negocios en lugar de ver al gobierno como el único responsable en la toma de decisiones. Y el gobierno tiene muchas maneras de influenciar la voluntad y la capacidad de las empresas para competir de esta forma. Creo que si hacemos que los negocios se vean a sí mismos de forma diferente, y logran que otros los vean de forma diferente, podemos cambiar el mundo. Lo sé. Lo veo. Lo siento. Creo que los jóvenes, mis estudiantes de Harvard Business School, lo están entendiendo. Si podemos romper esta brecha, esta inquietud, esta tensión, este sentido de que no estamos fundamentalmente colaborando aquí en la conducción de estos problemas sociales, podemos resolverlo, y creo que, finalmente, hallaremos las soluciones. Gracias. (Aplausos)